Oh
hello thanks for tuning in I'm really
looking forward to this the hearing
everyone's response and sharing this
video which I'll talk about in a second
so I just want to do a few housekeeping
things so if you've been thinking about
doing the art of the art of circling
which is a year-long training in in the
art of facilitation
it's a facilitating and tuning in in the
ways that some of the ways that you see
here in in the videos it's a year-long
training you have about a week and a
half before it starts so let me know if
you want to talk about that send me an
email
it's my emails below also if I stab like
maybe one more space open to work with
clients one-on-one so I do deep
consulting and coaching work working
with people when I want so if you're
interested in that email me and I think
that's it for the housekeeping so
today's video I have such a rich rich
rich dialo goes with John Herve key and
Joe yo.hannes yeah you probably pretty
familiar with John berbay key from my
channel yo.hannes is may be less
familiar I have a couple of videos with
him already up from the wild back to me
johannes is he is a true high
daguerreian in the high daguerreian
sense there's a there's a there's a way
where I can really get this sense with
johannes that he embodies evokes has
been transformed by the spirit of
thinking in the deepest sense of the
word so I'm really excited to bring him
into the conversation in the dialogue
os--
and uh and and and of course John John
Vicki who's a cognitive scientists and
philosopher and professor who's been
doing work on the meaning crisis and we
came together to bring in dialogue
specifically with the intention of
looking at this history of the
understanding of being in the in in
metaphysics which includes nihilism and
and to getting a conversation with the
notion of of Jonathan thank yous the
meaning crisis I wanted to get those two
like that got this together cuz I wanted
to get those two things talking together
because they're so intimate for me so I
wanted to like really let the let those
dialogue together and of course they did
and it led to but led to levels of
understanding and ideas that I'm sure I
am going to be are gonna be accompanying
me and all the walks that I take and all
the people that I talk to you that lived
in me that's one of the things about
this sense of dialo gross is that on one
level it's like it's happening in the
conversation but then it keeps happening
like in my dreams and the way that I see
what I think about the tensions I hold
it's a it's an ongoing so now I'm going
thing that I find that I live in right
and this this this conversation
definitely have that sensibility value
so I'm continually grateful that I get
to have a life like but then I get to do
these things these extraordinarily
beautiful people and so thanks for
tuning in I look forward to hearing your
comments and enjoy
so it's it's good to see the two of you
again and thanks again guy for inviting
me to that that drop-in video drop-in
session on Sunday that was quite
wonderful enjoyed it a lot yeah drop in
I brought one I just appreciate it you
making the time and drop in so you seem
particularly dropped in exactly how to
put it else to put it but just a sense
of like you just will Punk I appreciated
it there's a lot of good questions from
that group a lot of good questions yeah
it's a good group yeah well I appreciate
them watching the series so I thought
maybe we could follow up on the
discussion that johannes and i had on
Heidegger and the questions around
science technology and spirituality I I
think that would be a good place to
begin
I'll pick up but and but guide we could
also weave it together with perhaps you
know the deal logos project broadly
construed that I think those two should
be brought into a deeper conversation
with each other and so I think that
would be a good place to pick up pick up
and sort of weave together what do you
guys think about that as a proposal for
going forward that sounds great
I could I could share to just some of my
thoughts about like kind of tensions or
questions that are I've been walking
around with this a couple things like
one is I just I I would like to get um
Piper's Heidegger's notion right about
about the technological age and the
history of being and he's been precisely
the history of metaphysics in
conversation with them with them in
nihilism and encompassing with all
believing crisis yes very much I think
in seeing because in my mind done one
level I think about it I'm like I don't
know if I actually have a different if
there's a difference there
but I've imagined there's some key
differences right but I just I would
love to get them talking to each other
and just I would imagine they would
deeply inform one another in ways that
were would be really that's really good
and I think you're honest I we didn't
finish I don't think we actually caught
around to the topic of Heidegger's
thesis that the history of metaphysics
is the history of nihilism I think we're
we were just sort of broaching on it am
I am I remembering that correctly I
think that's about where we were and
we're just about to get onto that and of
course the connection to the meeting
crisis I think is is is pertinent and
relevant I start off the whole section
on the the prophets of the meaning
crisis with Heidegger because I think
he's pivotal figure so yeah IIIi would
like to to talk about that and that goes
towards sort of the broader topic that
I'm trying to explore you know in this
and the new series I have voices with
Rob a key because I'm trying to get at
you know this relationship between
science spirituality and the meaning
crisis so that's that's one is getting
those talking to each other the other
one is just kind of attention I notice
I'm having in let's just come about and
it's um
it I was really I want one of these
Johannes I really enjoyed your
conversation with your last conversation
with your teacher about about nihilism
you would inaudible yeah yes excuse me
what was the name what was the name evil
ditching out oh yeah yeah um yeah I just
I just really enjoy him a lot like like
his rigor of thought but let is at the
same time just a real unique being well
but one of the things he talked about
was how do we you know you got that how
do we respond to the with all of being
right and and what is how do you respond
to that and and I think one of the
things I'm I notice I have a like a
a wandering or attention when I listen
to other people and what I think about
it myself is on one level I see a lot of
people so-called responding to it mm-hmm
right however it seems to me that in
some way the way that they're thinking
about it demonstrates the very embodies
the the in their response like furthers
the issue of Technology right kind of
like this notion of like turning the
world into a problem to solve
okay and just I just noticed like I I
think I have this sense of what
Heidegger's talking about with the with
temporality and like the understanding
of being is that it's it's actually we
are inside of it right right there's a
there's a quality of like that it's not
under our direct control and like that
there's something in there about and
given that right what is the authentic
response being immortal right in being
in touch with the actual phenomena so
that's like one of the things that I'm
noticing is and and just also thinking
about it in terms of like the ecology of
practices right right right
and and I and you're John you're you're
you're my understanding of your repeated
insistence that not to imply an auto
theology right yes like it's about the
process of exercising the machinery
correctly and like we don't need to
assert we don't need to cert a being
right or God or something but there's a
mystery and and tuchis that you can get
in it through the exercise of it right
and I I think there's like deep
parallels there but I did it irritated
with people a lot when they talk about
like this kind of mania of like it's up
to us to fix the world or something like
that you know and I there's a tension in
there for me so I mean they don't make
allow me to a couple issues I want to
frame and then maybe we'll
Yanis any issues he wants to frame so in
connection with your second point I'm
interested in putting into a more Claire
clear and clarifying discussion
relationship what the ontological
aspects the existential and the
psychological aspects of the meaning
crisis are and because in connection
with that Kris and I have been working
on an article for the side view on the
symptomology of the meaning crisis and
trying to develop that and then you know
I you probably know I think you've seen
this before you distinguish between sort
of reactive responses and reflective
responses and I think for the project
that we're trying to do I think that's
adequate but that pretty much sits sort
of the intersection that it needs to be
Peas they'll better between the
cognitive and the existential but it
doesn't get too much into the
oncological and I'd like to get that a
little bit clearer and that might be a
way of going back to the first point of
clarifying the relationship between the
meeting crisis and nihilism and then the
other point that came up was which was
appointing Honus and I were did talk
about quite a bit which is you know I'm
struggling for a verb here but it's not
quite adequate but something like the
Rican SEP xual ization but in in a very
profound way of sacredness and what does
that mean for us now and what
relationship does that have if to my
first question is sacredness a category
for example that cuts across the
cognitive the existential and the
ontological is that precisely what it's
supposed to do for us and therefore
trying to situate it within any one of
those categories is a mistake but if it
is a trans categorical like that then
what's our appropriate way of of
understanding and relating to it so
those are the two issues I'd like to
sort of try and get get clear about I'm
just one other thing in there that's
just the paper that you and Chris wrote
yeah
is so good we're gonna actually start
off our our our series of videos where
we go through the Platonic dialogues
winning paper because I think it it
frames it perfectly and grounds it and
you know in our time and related you
there's a way that you formulated the
problem which I just thought was I've
just been thinking about it ever since
which is the loss of the second person
like person modernity as the loss of the
other basically and in a particular kind
of way yes yeah that's right and I had
never thought about it quite like that
but there's something about just that
sense of where we're blind right to what
one presupposes what gives a die up a
genuine dialogue owes right and uh yeah
yeah I think that that goes towards both
my questions no surprise because you
know I'm posing the question that I
wrote the paper with Chris so but the
the idea that that the logos might
actually again cut across the three
categories and it might be a place in
which we're also finding a way of
reenacting and therefore reimagining in
Corbin sense of the word imagine the
imaginal reimagining the sacred and so
I'm I would like to talk about that in
connection to the two questions I raised
yeah let me just briefly may be
summarized with the Genaro and I talked
about some something else it was on
Nietzsche and Heidegger on definitions
of nihilism and for Nietzsche nihilism
is that beings are nothing beings are
senseless they amount to nothing while
and and that for Heidegger means that
Nietzsche here turns all of metaphysics
on its head but this metaphysician why
because he begins with beings and then
leaves to the beingness of
and then Heidi get in the second
Nietzsche book rights or argues that
authentic nihilism I'm like and nihilism
as' would mean not meaninglessness in
this sense that we usually how we
usually think of it but what mean that
being itself always already stays away
being itself amounts to nothing and
that's not a value judgment that's not a
moral problem but being it is always
already withdrawing and then what
metaphysics has perhaps you could say
failed to see or fail to understand is
that being itself is that which
withdraws self conceals self denies
itself and has instead posited the
beingness of beings right has ratified
being for example as a to come back to
what you mentioned join the unto
theology comes posits being as the
causal soui that means the ground that
causes itself and tries to give ultimate
grounds and here we have as Heidegger
also says in connection to Sciences
which try to give the perfect you know a
ground for all beings whereas what we
perhaps in exercise can learn we should
learn is that ground always withdraws
that it's temporal is historical yeah so
those are just a couple of thoughts
maybe it's a beginning so one quick one
connection well maybe we can pick up we
don't have to do it immediately on that
cuz I'm interested in nishitani steak on
that there's a religion and nothingness
insert a enters into a long sort of
reflection on that and he he makes the
argument that Asian particularly
Buddhist philosophy has an advantage
because it doesn't have an established
history of prioritising being over non
being and prioritizing actuality over a
possibility and that in fact Taoism and
Buddhism you see the aucd inverse
actually in he and he argues that it's
that kind of a bill
to stand on the inversion point between
the two metaphysics he talks about you
know that the pivot point and that's
where you're trying to get in your
thinking right and so you can pivot
between these two and you can get to
this place where you do this sort of
fundamental aspect shift on so you're
not changing if this is the right word I
don't even know the right word I
seriously don't even know if it's the
right word you're not changing the fact
of nihilism you're doing this sort of
fundamental aspect shift on it
yeah I mean from seeing it as some kind
of beat privation to seeing it as some
kind of deep affordance so I'd like I
think I think that's I'd like to pick up
on that too because I didn't ever get a
chance to talk about the Kyoto School in
this and it's really interesting because
I think they're they're doing some well
I particularly think there's Chinese
work is brilliant yeah to hide again
being in time says possibility stands
higher than actuality it's vaguely sky
this is the total it's an inversion of
the history of metaphysics Hey perfectly
clear actuality is higher than
possibility and actually subsumes
consumes all the possibility and that's
simply a dialectical version of
Aristotelian is intelligent and then
highly converts there's an hiding it you
know the cute school of course
originates because they did they go to
fiber can listen to Heidegger yeah wow
this is all of a sudden someone we can
actually also understand right you know
there's Heidi get in touch with Japanese
scholars throughout his life and there's
text a dialogue there up wish that he
synthesized from conversed conversations
he had over his lifetime with scholars
from Japan where he says we do live in
different houses because we live in
different languages but there can there
is still a neighborhood it wouldn't
speak of a house without the houses only
a house of it's a neighborhood with its
surroundings its landscape but another
house another village somewhere else
and there must be no I think this is why
Heidi girls it gives up even on the word
of philosophy but he says philosophy is
over it's yeah it's it comes to an end
now the thinking must break free and I
think this is this kind of
because European philosophy never had to
deal what we call metaphysics didn't
have to deal with Japanese thought it
didn't have to deal with Indian thought
much it was circling around itself and
blahblah absolute spirit
let me be your prophet but if now it has
to deal with it and hiding it breaks
free from this and that that's I think
where were we I think where we have to
go is to have this dialogue between
these different houses of meaning if you
like these different planes of existence
because exactly as you say it so they
don't think consider what we call
nihilism from a moral perspective I mean
we do bicho though this is dangerous
that don't go there don't go to once a
nothing but for someone like hide again
and for the Cure to school you begin
with there is nothing you have to accept
this withdrawal this denial concealment
however you refer to it and only then
all of us weirdly enough beings light up
again in their wealth because they no
longer attacked as standing reserve for
example notion that's a way of thinking
of beings as in terms of a beingness of
beings is something waiting to be
explode connected it's to connect it to
thinking of beings only insofar as they
act and picking up on this on the key of
actuality is you know how things act
right which is different right right
right from from how they are and in the
sense of both you know the phenomena are
they shine into infinity as you said
they're also withdrawing at the same
time yeah this is what I think even
Aristotle shied away from this because
Dunamis which is the word Dunamis is
potentiality in Greek we get the word
dynamics for that in English Dunamis
carries with itself nothingness because
it's not yet actualized and what is not
yet actualized is of course there's the
nothing or you know some version of it
lingering there but that's something the
the West or Western thoughts or Western
philosophy metaphysics cetera has been
scared off right away from a
both of you know I'm a big fan of
Neoplatonism but this is one area in
which I have a deep criticism of
neoplatonism and the nishitani makes it
of course nothingness because you see
for example in platanus that
potentiality becomes equated with evil
explicitly now that that had sort of a
that had an important call cultural even
ontological function because it gave up
it gave a locus for evil and therefore
rendered it in some sense metaphysically
intelligible right even saying that it's
a place of non intelligibility only
makes sense if you can situate it within
a field of intelligibility right and so
I get why I get why that was an
attractive idea right I see why that's a
very attractive idea why people work
adhere to it but I think I think what
I'm saying is I think it's converging
with your point is it permanently
besmirched you know potentiality with
you know the taint of the chaotic and
the evil and the demonic and that's why
it's very hard like when I'm even trying
to teach dynamical systems and which is
directly related to dynamic again but
when I try to say look you have to shift
and I you know I'll put a piece of chalk
on a table and I'll push it and I'll say
well why did it move you know say well
because you pushed it I said well but
why else did it move right and then look
at me and they look at me well you
wanted to move no no no no no not that
why did it move and there'll be a
silence for a while and in silence and
then when somebody will say well because
there was like open space in front of it
it's a aha so but why are you so fixated
on the event why can't you see the
constraints that make things possible as
opposed to the events that are making
things act right right so we like we
like even just trying to teach them
something you know this is up your
philosophy this is just trying to get
them to understand dynamical systems I
have to first I have to do this
metaphysical move at the beginning of
the class of getting them to break away
from regarding actuality as a synonym
for reality and just getting them to
break that in their mind then it takes
them some time to do it but once they do
it
I can i I can I can see the
Oh Oh and then you see all these and
then they realize all the possibilities
for addressing a lot of you know sort of
really tricky thorny problems I now have
a space in which you can address them
that you couldn't address them before
but it I'm only pointing out for this
because it's just so how pervasive this
way of thinking is and that's what I
like when I read religion religion and
nothing this for the first time it just
looked like it really blew my mind
because I thought heidegger's idea about
that Ichi just inverts but I didn't get
I needed something like nishitani to say
but what's different from the like just
the inversion what what's what's the
trans framing for you is one of my terms
of this looked like initiative me a sort
of a really so my first deep
understanding of what that might look
like in that that sense of you know what
that that exercise that you just said so
much demonstrates I think is is the is
the thing that Heidegger is getting at
which is about this whole techno
in-frame movement where it's it's almost
like it's like it at this time it figure
eise's everything right so like the
moment the moment the ground right or a
background it it just keeps figure a guy
like it's only valid if it's
positionable right locatable and it's
and that's the thing that's just really
I think I keep finding myself impressed
with that that that sense of know that
there's an intelligibility right there
is an understanding that that I'm inside
of right that organizes everything mmm
which that I don't um
it's not even personal it's something
I'm it's constituting and how things
make sense right until that motion word
that just just that there's that issue
where it's like well why do you always
just figure the events and you just have
to be up to date sit sit with them to be
able to see that there's a there's a
ground that allows for this that
withdrawals that you can't figure they
what that is very much can we can we
pick up on that because that goes
towards my was it my first question like
that understanding you're talking about
guy this is what this one I want to sort
of slow down on and try and zoom in on
because that's what I'm trying to get
out about you know something that's
trans categorical that somehow
encompasses it's not it's not orthogonal
to but it's not reducible to any one of
these categories so I'm reducible to the
cognitive or the existential more or the
ontological and I suggested to you that
maybe sacredness is like that and and I
think you're try it sounds to me lets me
speak very clearly carefully it sounds
to me like you're trying to point to a
kind of understanding a kind of
comportment to that kind of trans
categorical sacredness and i think that
we could touch on unpack that together I
think that would be very helpful because
I think that goes towards this issue
about you know what the meaning crisis
is and how it I agreed if we shouldn't
identify the meaning crisis with
nihilism
I think nihilism is a perennial aspect
there's a certain sense in which it is
now you know maybe to use your term guys
worked before grounded or more figured
for people and I would but I still don't
even want to equate that exactly with
the meeting crisis I would say something
like nihilism is an aspect of the
meaning crisis because when I when I'm
pointing for the meaning crisis I'm
trying to point to not just a kind of
what's the word like an event or Rights
I'm trying to point to also well I'm
trying to point to all three of these
categories I'm trying to point to the
psychological aspects I'm trying to
point to also the suffering the loss of
agency the distress alright I'm not just
pointing to a particular realization of
that's the right word about our
relationship to being trying to point
out that this this erodes into certain
fundamental aspects of how we try to do
how we how we try to find 'mentally make
sense
and a adopt agency in the world so it's
I think it's for me it's a it's a larger
category than just what is encompassed
by nihilism in both the popular sense
and and also I think the more profound
sense that we're talking about when
we're talking about sort of the the
kyoto school so so the meaning crisis
then is something distinctly modern
something of this epoch I think so
although I would want to say that there
was something deeply analogous to it in
the Hellenistic period that you have you
had something like that in which there
was you know pervasive sense this
connection of a loss of touch with
realness and there was and this is where
the whole metaphor of the philosopher as
the physician of the psyche comes into
prominence right and it's actually it's
actually the progenitor of most of our
cognitive therapies today comes out of
that particular meaning crisis and what
what was interesting was the culture was
able to sort of reconfigure philosophy
and what it meant and and then that had
impacts on religion that sort of seemed
to have alleviated a lot of the
suffering and the distress
whereas we seem to be in a place that's
worse off if I can put it that way
because of our disconnection from our
wisdom traditions we don't seem to have
access to the resources we need in order
to bring about the transformations that
are the analogous to what happened in
the Hellenistic period so in one sense
yes but yeah I'm gonna say that that's
how I'd answer that question yeah did
this just maybe a brought a point but
this maybe makes it more accessible what
what about it is that Heidegger means
when he speaks of the science forgets in
hide the Oblivion of forgetting of being
yeah being cut off from what you would
say these resources of wisdom yes
without being totally divided from and
so we try to make sense by accelerating
right over seeing ourselves as workers
or giving ourselves meaning but the
trouble kicking god says if you just
give meaning to ourselves or to
something we can throw away that meaning
the next day yes something deep oh it
conscious
posited by us which is the postmodern
subjectivity that tries to get that get
that done but that totally doesn't work
there's a paranoia that maybe kicks into
with with late modern subjectivity now
and and yeah and this sense of being and
count off I think is what perhaps even
what depression indicates worse all
right some well I was gonna say I was
gonna say I mean here's the clear
instance of where you know the
existential mode the wait okay so
there's an ontological thing there's our
relationship to being and then we get
our existential mode right obviously
picked up on by like regard but then you
see it connecting to psychological
factors because I mean the the cognitive
science on meaning says that one of the
biggest fun so we tend to emphasize our
culture likes to say that in fact we use
this as a synonym and it also shows
again this collapse into actuality that
we've been talking about right that what
that top my my might my life is
meaningful if I have a purpose and it's
this right it's the purpose all right
now having a sense of purpose in fact
does psychologically contribute to
meaning life but not as much as a sense
of mattering which is a sense of being
connected to something that is larger
than yourself that has a value
independent of your egocentric desires
all right and so that it so basically
what it does it to put it into a phrase
and this then takes it back into
kirkegaard you'll you'll see why in a
sec it challenged you to it challenges
you to aspire to transformation right
because they're the only way of
appropriately relating the only way of
connecting to something that you accept
is larger than yourself is through some
kind of transformation some kind of self
transcendence right
and so that mattering to people is
actually psychologically crucial but it
takes you into this existential project
of aspirate of the aspiration of self
transcendence and then that puts you
back into the ontological problem of
what the heck does self transcendence
mean in our ontology so that's what I
mean about how I see all three connected
maybe that's a good sort of case study
of exactly what I'm trying to talk about
here
it's yes well I just don't know just I
love what your what your put I love what
your possessed by John I'm sorry did I
just I didn't mean to do I get
overwhelming I just like it I I'm
actually feeling like I'm just a voice
for the the pregnancy of these
connections speaking themselves write
that like the way that the cognitive and
the existential and the ontological are
all they're not identical claiming that
I'm not doing a reduction here but you
see how they're interdependent and
therefore the problem if that's the
right word of look for what would the
issue that we're trying to address is
not one that can simply be addressed by
therapy or even by philosophy in the
academic sense yeah no no no it must be
back in the palace it must be back in in
where where philosophy always were
strongest yes yes back in the call it
public sphere whatever but it meets and
it needs to be right when you speak off
but this sense that I matter but I met
her because there's something else that
matters more than than just I yeah a
true sense of all a sense of dangerous
divinities yes I like that you know God
isn't the reason with a capital r and we
all bow down to our own magnificent
powers but there's something what Heidi
could keep score talking about the
uncanny right yes the uncanny of the
world and this is not a moral statement
this is to say there is something
uncanny even just about existence the
sheer fact isset e of existence is
uncanny
but that uncanny Nez is an imitation
that on cane is an invitation to think
after what's actually going on and
that's what's very important to me is is
memory is shared if you like in English
I think as you could say something like
a shared sense of memory that's larger
than just my memory I'm gonna gonna be
leaping around a bit now so apologies
for that but when you think of how
transhumanism for exam
tries to sell us immortality which would
mean that all our memories get shared in
the cloud that that's a copy of yourself
that's probably not how I would think
how memory works I think that memory is
much larger it's shared as a extend
itself that you were thrown into and you
share in that a sense of memory that we
are being cut off from because we are
basically encapsulated isolated pinned
down just on us just me and it's just my
subjectivity that matters I I'm the
ground of my world transformations just
about optimizing myself in order to get
better in order to achieve this and that
but it's never or not often at least
getting back to a certain sense of
understanding again what what are the
fundamental questions of for example
existence and if we do so and that that
would have to accept however finitude
and death and and also certain
powerlessness not an entire
powerlessness but to a certain degree of
powerlessness in the face of existence
itself so that's interesting so there's
two things I want to bring up about that
then so a question is a relationship
between Heidegger sense of the uncanny
and Otto sense of the numinous which
Chris and I talk about them quite a bit
they're both post content so it's not
completely irrelevant yeah and and then
the what but that has to do with again
with this this this thing I'm talking
about the sacredness because presumably
the sacred wood would do exactly what I
said it would give you the psychological
muttering that puts you into the correct
existential mode of aspiration right
that then also gave you a sense of an
affordance of self transcendence that
wasn't just subjective projection that
was in some set had some kind of
connectedness to reality to it and so
that's again helps me to sharpen that a
little bit and so what role does the
like is the uncanny light
numinous or are they just different ways
of the same thing and then what did and
again what that has to do with the
collective memory because one thing I
see religions doing and this has come
out in my discussions with Paul van der
clay is they represent a distributed
cognitive memory of encounters with the
sacred right and and that it's not it
doesn't belong to any one person
precisely that was the holy idea of
ecclesia the body of Christ right it's
it's a car it's a distributed thing
across time and John Kahrs really talks
about this a lot in his book the
religious case against belief where he
said we've lost that sense of you know
what what you actually have you have
like this this I don't know what to call
it it's this sort of structure that
keeps forming around mystery and it sort
of carries it forward and that's how
it's remembered and then we're losing
that as we're trying to solidify and
still it in two sets of beliefs but the
point I'm trying to make is that the
church is that I'm using the church as a
categorical things I don't mean like the
Roman Catholic Church right it seems to
me that one of the places in which you
get a clear instance of where cultures
have tried to maintain that distributed
collective memory of the encounter with
the uncanny or what I might call the
sacred Rite and and to try and
continually bridge between the cognitive
the existential and the ontological has
precisely been in religions religions in
fact seem to be where you get that kind
of distribute not only distributed
synchronically across people but
diachronic ly across time this is the
whole religious idea of tradition right
tradition seems to be that kind of thing
you're talking about or or am I making a
mistake so I'm hoping on it no yeah a
tradition yes it's and the trouble is
hiding as one and one of the essays
that's not very well known behind it is
on traditional language and technical
language and it happens I hiding it
greatly in language we speak more and
more and in terms that are very
technical and
not no longer connected to the sense of
poesis employees and of course it's
connected to the sacred because the
sacred means is I would think means
something that you you simply to let
something occur to let something be let
something shine in of itself and not
want it to be in sheer available
actuality for example um and about also
there's a friend of mine francesca
cottony which is published a book on
Ottawa Nietzsche in Italian which is
presented early they the presence of the
gods right right and for also there
there is this sheer presence of the
divine in in beings and I'm not sure so
with with Heidegger I think it's a bit
different because for him the guards
remain unnamed and they remain withdrawn
a bit to a certain degree and I think
he's trying to do at least on my reading
I'm not sure if that's correct but he's
trying to do in the four fold is to
remind us think about when he writes
this fifties and sixties he gives public
talks to engineers etc he tells at a
time when there was a great believed
that technology could save us liberate
us once and for all we could have utopia
and adora at the time and and love
talked about how utopia would come about
when we finally give up on death right
so once we become him also that's when
we have utopia well when death becomes
an option for those who want to die for
whatever reason but in that time I think
he reminds the human being of a simple
truth of this capacity of being mortal
and that capacity is only however
possible to even think off when there
are immortals for Heidegger you can
never think one without the other right
there's there's this so in hi I'm Kenny
in Trevor no I'm means moon homely
unholy so the world is unholy but it can
also be homely and yeah that's what I
wanted to get to you know okay because
one of the things you know that Chris
and I thought about is that the sacred
seems
be doing both of these it seems to both
be a way of homing us against horror
this is geertz's notion right of the
sacred well at the same time also at
times as you say I'm homing us putting
us outside of that that sense and it
immediate between Ok Go Ahead
it's just like this is super because one
of the things I've been thinking about
is horror yeah exactly exactly yeah
horror is so important because the way
we think of horror is I mean just you
know everyday terms horror is a movie
yeah yeah horror is something in a film
that's horrible for two hours and then I
go home and maybe I have a bad dream but
no horahora
and the weird thing is what happens
again thanks to mono economy not thanks
then how does he define boredom he calls
boredom the horror mark we the horror of
emptiness which is that perhaps a ride
in the horse cart is is rather dull
right is incredibly bourgeois a
definition of horror
but that horror of our cuy but he's
almost like because the Newman oh what's
that
what's the nur woman on the the unnamed
that's what it means when cardless -
he's pushing even the essence of things
all the way to an an unnamed outside -
in realm of uncanny maybe to hell off of
sheer horror - you know HP Lovecraft you
could think of him for example here but
but when you think of this in terms of
Heidegger again in terms of the history
of metaphysics metaphysics forgets
consumer metaphysics forget self
withdrawal maybe metaphysics also
forgets horror
maybe this history forgets this sheer
horror that also is at the heart of
existence not only but also well that
gives need to two connecting points is
the way to go back to circle effect
immortality the way Eastern if there
were easy attic religions I'm thinking
you know especially you know Indian and
Chinese especially Buddhist but but
there's the horror of immortality yes
right
which so you know when I talk to people
in the West about this and I say I try
to get them to understand this idea
about the about how important your
mortality is well no but you know we all
know they'll say they'll say as if it's
axiomatic but we all just want to live
forever and I say well actually you
don't and that's not true about the
cultures right other cultures actually
experience the prospect of immortality
as deeply deeply horrific and and you
know you reincarnation for example is
the thing you're trying to break free
from in many versions of Hinduism and of
CO and the same thing with sort of the
desire for perpetual existence is what
binds you into suffering within Buddhism
in profound ways and so I think I think
what I'm trying to whatever the
connection I'm trying to bring it back
to you is I think the absence of horror
in our metaphysics is actually a telling
thing I think it again points to the
fact that we are ultimately seeking a
kind of security for our intelligibility
rather than always trying to nourish our
intelligibility through all and I think
those are fundamentally different
projects for us and that's the the the
security I think I and this is where I
think what the response to is I'd agree
to say the withdrawal of being through
the withdrawal of sense right and and
one of the things I liked in that
interview with your teacher he where he
was talking about the our response right
what is to to the withdrawal of sense is
is a is it is to take this hyper
morality position right oh great inside
it where we go we we experience the loss
of sense but we don't we don't recognize
we we we we compensate for it by just
being really upset of
about things right and being offended
about things and what you're saying is
you can notice that like rationality
doesn't have it doesn't even consider
rationality no no in that that that
responds to the to the withdrawal of of
the sense of beingness of the of the
fullness of things we we've excluded
from our notion of rationality any sense
of this whole side of the spectrum if I
could put it that way
rationality has has been truncated to
confirmation coherence the idea that
insight and transformation and a
capacity for wonder in Plato's sense not
Aristotle sense because I think for
Aristotle it's for my curiosity for
Plato it's clearly awe that all of these
things are actually crucial to
forgetting for example overcoming all of
this self-deception that our ego
centrism and our narcissism makes us
pray to and they should therefore be
central central to our ideas of
rationality not peripheral things that
are somehow romantically pursued when
our rationality is done what it needs to
do for the day I think that is a very
crucial point what you just did god to
try and that way in which we're talking
again this is again we're talking about
something ontological and then we shift
into the existential and then it
reverberates back into the cognitive now
because now we're bringing up the whole
notion of what what does rationality
because if if this is about you know
sense making rationality should be in
this discussion but obviously in a
reformulated way so that it comports
with what we're talking about well and I
think one of the things that I'm if I
feel into it like if I I think one of
the things I like about um about real
what I've gotten out of reading
Heidegger more than his ideas or his
views and it's been to read them is to
walk on the path of looking to that
which reveals it's uncanny nasai wanted
to ask you about that yeah it's a almost
like it's been a practice for me
well holy but I have found that to be
the case and I think I did what I had to
go would actually like me saying this so
there's maybe a bit of a a performative
pun here I found that to be the case
with all of the really great
philosophers like I find you don't read
Spinoza yeah you you base you you you
you I don't know what you immerse
yourself in Spinoza until like you you
I'm gonna use this for because I think
it's appropriate you have to read you
have to reads for knows you have to
recite to knows it to yourself
religiously you have to you have to go
through like if you don't get scan to
get to atiba when you're reading if it
doesn't occur to you then I use all and
all you've got is the arguments of
Spinoza
I think you've missed the ethics I think
you didn't missed the ethics yeah same
thing with Plato right for like Plato is
sacred to me because like I think I can
keep following Plato
I can I can go to Plato I get insight I
get transfer get the challenge to
transformation I go out in the world the
world discloses itself to me in a way
that it couldn't before that transforms
me I go back to Plato and then I see
something again in Plato that I didn't
see and I can and so Plato engenders and
agog a Spinoza
engenders can see Intuit Eva I think the
great philosophers engender again this a
state that's between and beyond the
cognitive the existential and the
ontological they put you into this place
I'm struggling for words here that isn't
captured by those categories and that's
the thing of any great philosopher is to
get to that place with them right and
that's in mm right I think how to do it
like that
sorry guide you but the great
philosophers yeah it's I think what
you're describing is what you could call
the apparition of thinking right this
didn't yes there's nothing and this is
this is what I thought philosophy would
be yes yes khadeem yeah and it was a bit
like that medieval ditch and I don't
need to leave but it's because it's very
small University and I came here and it
was a bit
friend but it's it's yeah I think that's
ultimately how philosophy should be
taught but I don't care is it this isn't
but that isn't that's not ultimately
that important it's not that important
what by the way you might disagree with
Plato and some things of others but what
is it then why is it these texts and the
way we do and what is it that they do
with us and why do we why is it that we
can come back to them again and again
and the gamut must actually I've read
the cave at aghori I don't know how many
time exactly exactly
still I'm reading it I could read every
week and I would still all right I
forgot oh really this is every single
time that yes yeah God back to you
because I cut you off I'm sorry about
that I just was wondering if we look at
I think I really want to like I think
this is exciting because it's drawing I
think it maybe bringing something
together if we look at what is it that
happens in that relationship of reading
of philosopher right like what are we
exercising and I'm wondering if it
touches it on the ontological like the
cognitive and the existential these
thrilling so that's that's what I'm
saying and and then and then for me and
of course you probably first saw that I
was going to do this guy this then
translates also into deer logos as
something that's happening between
people and also has that and so there's
something right there and it's no
coincidence that you know Plato writes
dialogues right that it's not a
coincidence that is not a coincidence
there's something about what we're doing
here and how you should read a
philosopher they need each other this is
what I mean about when you know this
work this is a deep meaning of what I'm
trying to I'm trying to work on with you
guy about trying to bring
philosophy a-- not academic philosophy
but philosophy a-- into like into
circling and to get the two of them you
know working together you know the
what's happening in the circling feeds
into reading the philosophers and
reading the philosophers feeds back into
that that's
that's that's the project I'm alright
now exam with you right does all the
text they send you
yeah I did Chester was bought the last
one you gave me I'm sorry it was R it
was very good by the way it was very
good so I think that I think the thing
about well it's actually like bringing
in the conversation that he had with
Andrew what I was writing with you about
a second conversation a conversation I
really really got at a deeper level this
this sense of what was it um how
rationality is rationing for where to
bring your attention that reveals wisdom
right
yeah the rationing and the ratty oh yeah
to me that it's it has as much to do
with logistics as it does to do with
logic yeah and and and and and the
proportioning is it's like just a copy
it isn't just an intellectual
proportioning it's like it's like in the
four fold the correct proportioning of
human beings to the gods and to the
earth
that's ratty oh right that's right here
right because it's closer to it's much
closer like I say to logos and all that
was you know the best best word from
another culture is Dharma Dharma is a
word like in Buddhism that has all of
that kind of sense do it right yes and
that just I just really just got that
sense of oh that there's a way that
there's a way of listening right that
there's a way it seems like listening
seems to be the right metaphor here
right I like harkening better
I like your harkening better because for
me harkening carries with it the sense
of also a receptivity and and and a
making one's oneself sensitive lul most
vulnerable and opening and listening
doesn't connote that for me the way
harkening de because hearken ii like
it's a bit in your harken is a
all to you right listen to the call and
that there's something about it where is
where I think this is starts to Britt
this is starts to be break free of the
metaphysics right mmm because it's it to
here is is to be unclear about what
you're hearing but yet to be a tune to
what you can't quite make out yet right
that would whispering to you and to to
be or because this is one of things I
noticed encircling and leading circling
of just I noticed this last weekend is
just sitting with people and and
harkening so what is the what are they
what what's really present what's really
present and just good evening into that
is I can I kept feeling this sense of in
this growing sense of tuning in to the
movement of showing or something like
that
that's in is there's an orientation that
just keeps drawing it it has an auto
poetic quality to it guys
object is not looking for an object or
an answer it's something else just at
the edge of intelligibility or it
reminds me I was circling last night it
remind I so I said I want to follow the
circle where it goes but I was invoking
Socrates is a point of follow the
argument wherever it goes that that's
that's the that kind of sense yeah I
wanna I want to hear what you wanted us
to say but I want to ask you one
question guy first
so and this goes to the point we were
just on I don't want to leave you yet
because I sort of brought this up like
sort of post circling I would say saying
you know we're hearkening to each other
and we're even harkening you know to the
third factor that's opening between us
but but it seems to me there's another
like I said you know I have an
allegiance to to you the people are
circling with an allegiance to or the
process but I also want to be able to I
think this is part of being an
authentically participating it I want to
be able to engage my allegiance to the
topics that might emerge
yes so for example one one person sort
of brought up sort of brought the
circling practice itself into question
yeah
right and what happened is people just
did the circling and they sort of tune
into each other and I was kind of like
you know no I didn't that no no no no
that's a no that's a lost opportunity
you know we we should keep the circle
going but they're you know that person
wants to wonder about circling rather
than just wonder within circling and
those aren't the same thing and they
should be put into a dialogue with each
other and you know what is it what does
that mean like to subtract and like and
you know and then what happened is we
didn't started this discourse around
circling which you know that's what I
mean about again trying to get these
things to talk to each other we should
both let Johannes say something though
he's been very patient and kind with us
I think just briefly on harkening I had
not thought of this I'd always just you
know use the word to listen to I will
from now on say harken it's also much
closer to Hulk and
Hulk right which is listen
but harken in a proper that you have to
now really hear what I'm saying yes and
what we now think of as the third where
we've classified as the first fragment
of Heraclitus livid actually was his
first fragment we don't know he speaks
of a cooing he speaks of the logos and
that we yes yes we are in a hearing
stance to the MILCON yeah yeah but we're
not listening or now I would say
harkening yeah so this is one of the
oldest wisdoms that we have or
right testimonials of logos is that
logos can be hearkened there's something
as always a hearing that's always
something addressing us calling us yeah
but what we must do is respond we must
respond and that's ultimately
beautifully in English to say this
because you can say that's
responsibility yes there is this deep
sense of responsibility
you mustn't be cut off from and it has
to do Altima Lee I think with with with
the ecstatic temporalities of history
itself that's something that I that I
see in encircling happening because it
works with what has been comes back
towards you the old time right this is
all the time and I think this is how
this really works itself and what what
we've done is we've we've made linear
history and assume that we just move on
into an empty feel that we can that will
rearrange and make make it just around
where we please and we've completely
forgotten that that which has been is
still coming back and maybe not just you
know to haunt us but also to give us
again a sense of direction